# JAMES RUTLEDGE

PHONE +1 512 423 8906 GITHUB github.com/jmz527

EMAIL jarutledge2@gmail.com

PERSONAL jamesaaronrutledge.com

LINKEDIN linkedin.com/in/jmz527

CHMMADV

I am a full-stack web developer with over five years experience, a homegrown steady diligence and a raw passion. I thrive on complexity, revel a challenge, and I have a reservoir of patience (handy for those deep dives). If you are looking for a composed codesmith with an acute eye for detail – then take note!

**EXPERIENCE** 

September 2015 – Present

## **ENERGY METRICS**

Software Developer | New York, NY

- Led front-end development for EM's enterprise data center software solution.
- Built several interactive data visualization widgets from scratch using only jQuery and VanillaJS.
- Created dynamic tree structures for data manipulation based on parasitic combination inheritance.
- Collaborated with a team of .NET developers to seamlessly integrate front-end layer with ASP.NET.
- Implemented dozens of JavaScript & jQuery libraries.
- Gave presentations on prototypal inheritance, templating engines, CSS pre-compilers.

April 2015 – July 2015

## GENERAL ASSEMBLY

Full-Stack Web Development Student | Austin, TX

- 13 week full-time intensive course on full-stack web development.
- Studied programming fundamentals, responsive design, objectoriented programming, product development, & agile workflow.
- Led a group in building a restaurant review app using Ruby on Rails & PostgreSQL.

October 2010 – January 2013

# MIND WINK

Co-Founder/Web Developer | Austin, TX

- Designed & built websites using Drupal, Wordpress, gained an indepth understanding of front-end development practices.
- Participated in pitch-meetings, developed presentations, established agile project management system & managed projects.
- Established cross-promotional campaigns with local businesses and developed company brands.

January 2008 – September 2015

## **FREELANCE**

Web Developer | Austin, TX

- <u>PiqMapper</u>, a social analytics app allowing users to track their well being, over time, using colors. Built with NodeJS & MongoDB.
- <u>TurnPlot</u>, a social platform, virtual grid, and digital space to cultivate personal brands. Built using RubyOnRails & PostgreSQL.
- <u>EcoRise Youth Innovations</u>: Worked closely with founder to develop & maintain PHP website. Pro bono.
- The Hub Cyclery: WordPress installation with a custom theme. Designed, built & maintained.

EDUCATION

GENERAL ASSEMBLY

Web Development Immersive | Austin, TX

Graduated August 2014

Graduated

July 2015

University of Texas

B.A. English, Minor in Film | Austin, TX

SKILLS

### LANGUAGES

JavaScript, Ruby, SQL, HTML5, CSS3, SASS, LESS, JSON, XML, Bash

#### Frameworks + Libraries

Node]S, ¡Query, React]S, Ruby on Rails, AJAX, Twitter Bootstrap, Highcharts, Backbone]S, Sinatra, Wordpress, Drupal, D3

#### METHODOLOGIES

Agile Development, MVC Design Patterns, Responsive Design, Object-Oriented Programming, Search Engine Optimization, Test-Driven Development

#### OTHER TOOLS

Git, GitHub, Heroku, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Grunt, Gulp, Bower, Webpack, cPanel, Chrome DevTools, Adobe Creative Suite, Sketch

INTERESTS

- Web Development
- Film
- Travel
- Literature
- Art
- Cooking

FUN FACTS

- I was once hospitalized in Thailand after visiting a Buddhist monastery.
- I have been to Japan, S. Korea, Spain, Italy, Greece, Turkey, Switzerland, Mexico, and throughout the Caribbean.
- I live in Chinatown and 我会说汉语。
- One time I watched all three Lord of the Rings films back-to-back...the extended editions.
- I can juggle.